Pham Anh Cuong

Masdar City, Abu Dhabi, UAE

💌 cuong.pham@mbzuai.ac.ae 🛗 anhcuong-pham 🞧 pacman-ctm 🔗 pacman-ctm.github.io

Background and Research Interests

My research interests focus on Machine Learning theory (especially Mathematics for Machine Learning), based on the motivation to analyze the way Machine Learning and Deep Learning models work from my previous working experience as an AI Engineer/Data Scientist, and also from my ten years as a Mathematics competitor. I also share an interest in the Applications of AI.

Education

Mohamed bin Zayed University of Artificial Intelligence (MBZUAI)

08/2024 - present

Abu Dhabi, UAE

MSc in Machine Learning

- Supervised by Dr. Samuel Horváth (primary) and Dr. Nils Lukas (co-supervisor).
- Studying Optimization for Machine Learning, also a bit of Federated Optimization.

VNU University of Engineering and Technology (VNU-UET)

08/2019 - 06/2023

Hanoi, Vietnam

BS in Information Technology (Honors)

- Graduated with High Distinction (GPA 3.71/4.0 or 8.77/10 top 5% of CS department) [Transcript].
- Thesis: "Building a Vietnamese image captioning dataset and developing a visual-text transformation model for generating image captions" (in Vietnamese) (9.5/10).
- Supervised by Assoc. Prof. Quang-Thuy Ha, Dr. Van-Quang Nguyen (co-sup), MSc. Thi-Hong Vuong (co-sup).

Phan Boi Chau High School for the Gifted

08/2016 - 05/2019

High school diploma, Specialized in Mathematics

Nghe An, Vietnam

• Attended Vietnam Mathematical Olympiad (VMO) for high school students (2019).

Experience

Data Scientist

Viettel Networks

10/2023 - 07/2024

Hanoi, Vietnam

Hanoi, Vietnam

- Researching and applying Computer Vision (image processing, segmentation, classification) in telecommunication.
- Solving big data problems (using Machine Learning with GPUs) for optimizing and automating with large-scale data, from 100M to 1B records (in telecommunication).

DSKT Laboratory, VNU-UET

09/2021 - 09/2023

Student Research Intern

- Studied about Multi-view Time Series Forecasting.
- Project: Continual Learning in Natural Language Processing. This project applied a prototype augmentation mechanism to consistent representation learning to reduce saving data for the next phase of continual learning but still alleviate the forgetting problem [$Paper\ C1$].
- Thesis Project: Image Captioning in Computer Vision. This project created a new image-caption dataset in Vietnamese and evaluated it with the best-performance Image Captioning models for English at that time [Paper P1].

Giaohangtietkiem JSC

05/2022 - 08/2023

Hanoi, Vietnam

R&D Engineer

- Researched and developed a mail spam filtering based on Deep Learning methods, achieving the f1-score of 90% after training with 50k emails, it was then deployed to the company's internal email system.
- Learning about chatbot architecture.
- MasterDev Season 4 Internship Program in Research and Development domain Training about Probability & Statistics, Natural Language Processing, some Big Data frameworks such as Hadoop and Spark (05/2022 - 08/2022).

Honors and Awards

Fully-funded Master's scholarship at MBZUAI

2024

Third Prize in Linear Algebra (for rank 4-6), UET Mathematical Olympiad

2021, 2022, 2023

Yamada Scholarship Excellent Scholarship for top highest GPA from VNU-UET 2022 2021

Skills

Programming Languages: Python, Java, C, C++ (all usable), HTML/CSS, JavaScript, MySQL (all basic) Technologies and Frameworks: PyTorch, Linux, Docker (usable), Hadoop, Spark, Laravel (all basic)

Additional Working Skills: Microsoft Office, LaTeX, Git

Communication: Vietnamese (native), English (with TOEIC LR 855, IELTS 7.0).

Publications

- [C1] Quynh-Trang Pham Thi, Anh-Cuong Pham, Ngoc-Huyen Ngo and Duc-Trong Le, "Memory-Based Method using Prototype Augmentation for Continual Relation Extraction," 2022 RIVF International Conference on Computing and Communication Technologies (RIVF), Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam, 2022.
- [P1] Anh-Cuong Pham, Van-Quang Nguyen, Thi-Hong Vuong, Quang-Thuy Ha, "KTVIC: A Vietnamese Image Captioning Dataset on the Life Domain." arXiv preprint arXiv:2401.08100.

References

• Dr. Samuel Horvath, Assistant Professor at MBZUAI (UAE)

• Dr. Nguyen Van Quang, Researcher at RIKEN AIP (Japan)

• Dr. Ha Quang Thuy, Associate Professor at VNU-UET (Vietnam)

∠ thuyhq@vnu.edu.vn **ℰ** Website